Audley Moore: FOIA File (United States Federal Bureau of Investigation) TAM.410
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Audley Moore: FOIA File (United States Federal Bureau of Investigation)
1940s-1960s, undated
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation
Pinto, Earl
TAM.410
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Audley (Queen Mother) Moore was an African American black nationalist and communist. In the 1920s she was active in Marcus Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association in New York City. In 1936 she joined the Communist Party, becoming secretary of its Harlem section in 1941, and in 1942, secretary of the New York State Party organization. She left the Party in 1950, and subsequently founded the Universal Association of Ethiopian Women, In 1959 tutored the young Malcolm X, in 1963 she established a Reparations Committee to advocate compensatory payment to descendants of slaves, and in 1968 participated in the declaration of the Republic of New Africa and initiated its statement of independence. The collection contains FBI files, and documents Audley Moore's political activity and views from the 1940s through the 1960s.
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Earl Pinto in 2007. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.013.
Arrangement
Organized into one series: FOIA FBI Files, which are arranged by file number.
Historical/Biographical Note
Audley (Queen Mother) Moore, an African American black nationalist and communist, was borh in 1898 in New Iberia, Louisiana, in 1891. In 1919 she joined Marcus Garvey's black nationalist movement, and in the 1920s, moved to New York City to work in Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association. In 1936 she joined the Communist Party, was active in its Harlem section, becoming its secretary in 1941, and in 1942, secretary of the New York State Party organization. In the late 1940s she began to assert the African American national question within the Party, and left the Party in 1950. In the 1950s she founded the Universal Association of Ethiopian Women, in 1959 tutored the young Malcolm X, in 1963 she established a Reparations Committee to advocate compensatory payment to descendants of slaves, and in 1968 participated in the declaration of the Republic of New Africa and initiated its statement of independence.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
There are two interviews with Moore in the Tamiment Library's Oral History of the American Left collection (Oral Histories 2)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains FBI files, and documents Audley Moore's political activity and views from the 1940s through the 1960s.
Women communists -- United States.; Communism -- New York (State).; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Reparations for historical injustices |z United States.; African American communists.; Black nationalism |z United States.; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965; Moore, Audley, 1898-1997; Communist Party of the United States of America (New York); Republic of New Africa (Organization); Universal Association of Ethiopian Women; Pinto, Earl
- FOIA FBI Files (Box 1)
  - File 100-13205 A.S., 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - File 100-13205 VCD, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - File 100-11631/1, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - File 100-11631/2, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - File 100-17241/1, May, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - File 100-17241/2, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - File 100-12344, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - File 12344, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - File 100-HQ-61122: List of Files for Destruction, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - File 100-13205 BHB, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - File 100-13205 KOB, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - File 100-13205 PMC, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - File 100-13205 DJ, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - File 100-13205 MLV, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - File 100-13205 NHK/1-2, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - File 100-12069/1, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - File 100-12069/2, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - File 100-13205 LEJ, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - File 100-13205 AJW, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - File 100-3751/1-2-3, 1958, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - File 100-3751/4, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - File 100-46185, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - File: Unnumbered A, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - File: Unnumbered B, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - File: Unnumbered C, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - File: Unnumbered D, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)